Finding Aid for the Alice Greenfield McGrath Papers LSC.1490
UCLA Library Special Collections
Alice Greenfield McGrath papers
1917-2009
UCLA Library Special Collections
McGrath, Alice
LSC.1490
6.5 Linear Feet (13 boxes, 3 oversize boxes)
Alice McGrath (1917-2009) was a political activist who first became known for her work to overturn the improper convictions of Mexican American youth in Sleepy Lagoon Trial in which the defendants were tried as a group under inhumane conditions. McGrath also supported humanitarian efforts and revolution in Nicaragua, pro bono work through the Mexican American Bar Association, and taught courses on self defense. The collection consists of trial documents, correspondence, articles, awards, photographs, and other ephemera.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. All requests to access special collections materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL AND DIGITAL MATERIALS: This collection contains both processed and unprocessed audiovisual and digital materials. Audiovisual and digital materials are not currently available for access, unless otherwise noted in a Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note at the series and file levels. All requests to access processed audiovisual materials must be made in advance using the request button located on this page.
Provenance/Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alice McGrath, 1986; additions to collections gifted by Alice McGrath in 1990, 1995, and 2003.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 9922214073606533
Biography
Alice Greenfield McGrath (April 5, 1917-November 27, 2009) was a political activist who first became known for her work to overturn the improper convictions of Mexican American youth in Sleepy Lagoon Trial in which the defendants were tried as a group under inhumane conditions. McGrath also supported humanitarian efforts and revolution in Nicaragua, pro bono work through the Mexican American Bar Association, and taught courses on self defense.
Alice Greenfield McGrath was born in Calgary, Canada to a family of Russian Jewish immigrants. At the age of 5, McGrath and her family moved to Los Angeles. McGrath's experience growing up as an immigrant heavily influenced her later involvement in social activism. After graduating high school, McGrath worked several jobs including working in a candy factory and as a sales representative for Grove Press.
At the age of 24, Alice McGrath began volunteering for the defense committee of the Sleepy Lagoon Trial, now widely known for unjustly convicting an entire group of young Mexican-American youth with little evidence and many human rights violations. Several months later, she was appointed executive secretary. Though she was not directly involved in the legal work on the case, she worked tirelessly to raise awareness about the trial, coordinate efforts. Of particular note is McGrath's effort to correspond with and visit the defendants in prison. In October 1944 the committee's work paid off, and Judge Clement Nye overturned the convictions. The case then became a foundation for legal decisions nationwide concerning defendants' rights.
Alice Greenfield McGrath's direct involvement in the case led playwright Luis Valdez to contact her and buy the rights to her character. In l978, Zoot Suit, a play by Luis Valdez based on the sleepy lagoon case and the servicemen riots premiered at the Mark Taper Forum with much acclaimed success. The play is a fictionalized account of the trial. Alice McGrath becomes the central character. A film rendition of the play makes headlines in the l980s.
In 1952, she married Thomas McGrath, a poet and teacher. During this time, both came under surveillance by the FBI for their political ideologies and community activism. This investigation led to Thomas McGrath being summoned to appear before the Un-American Activities Committee.
Around 1957, Alice McGrath met Bruce Tegner, her son Daniel's self-defense instructor. Based on her son's experience, McGrath enrolled in Tegner's courses, earned various titles, and began working with Tegner to write books on self-defense. She later taught self-defense courses at various community centers and colleges around Southern California.
In addition to her career, McGrath continued to volunteer her time toward political and humanitarian efforts. She made numerous trips to Nicaragua during and after the Sandinista National Liberation Front overthrow of the Somoza government. She led clergy, physicians, lawyers, and teachers on tours through the country and helped raise money to buy medicine for Nicaraguan hospitals and Hurricane Mitch victims, her humanitarian work also continued in the United States, where she became the coordinator of the Pro Bono department of the Mexican American Bar Association.
Alice McGrath died on November 27, 2009 at the age of 92 from complications of a chronic illness.
Scope and Content
The collection consists of trial documentation, correspondence, publicity materials, photographs, articles, books, and ephemera.
The bulk of the material in the collection relates to the Sleepy Lagoon trial and its development into a play and film. In addition, documentation and photographs from McGrath's support of the Sandinista National Liberation Front and humanitarian work in Nicaragua constitute a large portion of the collection. The collection also includes personal photographs, awards, correspondence, and documentation of a trip to China.
Organization and Arrangement
Arranged in the following series:
Sleepy Lagoon trial
Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee
Zoot-Suit media adaptations
Personal papers
Correspondence
Writings
Miscellaneous
Photographs
Magazines, books, film scripts
China trip
Nicaragua
Awards and recognitions
Government investigation files
Self-defense
Related Oral Histories
The following oral histories are available through the UCLA Library Center for Oral History Research:
Interview of Alice McGrath [oral history transcript] / James V. Mink and Gerald Nash, interviewers. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 1981. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
The Education of Alice McGrath [oral history transcript] / Michael Balter, interviewer. UCLA Library Special Collections, Center for Oral History Research interview, 1987. Available at UCLA Library Special Collections, Charles E. Young Research Library, UCLA.
Related Material
Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee Records (Collection 107). Available at the Library Special Collections, UCLA.
Nicaragua -- Social conditions -- 20th century.; Los Angeles (Calif.) -- Social conditions -- 20th century.; Mexican Americans -- Civil rights -- California -- Los Angeles.; Zoot Suit Riots, Los Angeles, Calif., 1943.; Women civil rights workers -- California -- Archives.; McGrath, Alice -- Archives; Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee (Los Angeles, Calif.); Valdez, Luis--; McWilliams, Carey
- 1. Sleepy Lagoon Trial., 1943-2008
  Scope and Contents note
  Contains documents pertaining to the trial, correspondence between Alice McGrath and the defendants, newspaper clippings, and ephemera and correspondence pertaining to the play and film adaptations of the events.
  - 1.1 Sleepy Lagoon Defense Committee., 1943-2005
    This subseries focuses on all documents pertaining to the actual historical trial.
    - Court documents -- police statements for the grand jury., 1943 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Court documents -- Copy of Appeal transcript and copies of chronology., 1943 June-1944 October 04 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Also includes a copy of "The Sleepy Lagoon Case" prepared for the Defense of Mexican-American Youth.
    - Ayres report., 1942 August 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
      Ed Duran Ayres Report laying out cultural arguments for Mexican youth's violent tendencies.
    - Sleepy Lagoon Committee letterhead and defendants' list., ca. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 4)
      Also includes letterhead with Zoot-suiter drawing by Delgado(?), autographed list of defendants and inmate numbers, and a copy of "The Sleepy Lagoon Mystery" by Guy Endore.
    - Correspondence between McGrath and the defendants while in prison., 1943 October 08-1944 June 26 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Appeal News vol. I and II., 1943 April 7-1944 March 04 (Box 1, Folder 6)
      Copies of bulletin published by Defense Committee to keep defendants and public aware of the case's latest news.
    - Greenfield (McGrath), Alice. "The Wearing of the 'drape' is no sign of delinquency." Daily News, 21 May 1945., 1945 May 21 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Greenfield (McGrath), Alice. "Mexicans called their home 'Maravilla'--at first." People's World, (?) 1945., ca. 1945 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Greenfield (McGrath), Alice. "Why Lupe doesn't go to school…" People's World, (?) 1943., ca. 1943 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Greenfield (McGrath), Alice. "The trial that was made a Pageant of Prejudices" and Greenfield (McGrath), Alice. "Hard Times for the boys.. ."., Circe 1945 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Letters written on behalf of the defendants., 1944 June 15 1945 February 02 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Various letters from Mexican consulate Peralta, and from Penafiel, editor of comite' contra el racismo and a single letter from Roberson and another single letter from Daniel G. Marshall from the Catholic Interracial Council of Los Angeles.
    - Photos of defendants., ca. 1943- (Box 1, Folder 12)
      Photos taken primarily in San Quentin State Prison and Chino State Prison (including autographed photo by defendants)
    - Photos of defendants' families., ca. 1944 (Box 1, Folder 13)
      Especially Leyvas's family.
    - Victory telegrams., 1944 October 4 (Box 1, Folder 14)
      Copies of telegrams notifying Henry Leyvas and Mrs. Anita of appeal's overturn decision.
    - Correspondence -- Mark Day to McGrath., 1973 December 22-1977 October 18 (Box 1, Folder 15)
      Letters written after the Sleepy Lagoon Case and one response by McGrath in 1973.
    - Endore, Guy. "Sleepy Lagoon Mystery." Los Angeles, Unidos Books and Periodicals: 1978. (reprint)., 1978 Oct (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Paul Fitzgerald. "George Sibley." Forum 6, no. 1 (July/August 1979):3-10, 30., 1979 July-August (Box 1, Folder 17)
      Interview with Shibley in response to the Zoot Suit Play by Valdez published by California Attorneys for Criminal Justice.
    - Barajas, Frank P. "The Defense Committees of Sleepy Lagoon: A Convergent Struggle against Fascism, 1942-1944." Aztlan: A Journal of Chicano Studies 31, no. 1: 33-62., 2006 (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Manuscript by Ralph Armbruster-Sandoval -- the stories we tell., 2008 April 22 (Box 1, Folder 19)
      Revised and later published as Armbruster-Sandoval, Ralph. "The Life of the Party: Alice McGrath, Multiracial Coalitions, and the Struggle for Social Justice." Aztlan: A Journal of Chicano Studies 36, no. 1 (Spring 2011): 69-98.
    - Alfredo Gonzalez's book outline., c. 1980 (Box 1, Folder 20)
      Preliminary title is: The Origins of Mexicano/Chicano Gangs: A Reconceptualization.
    - Manuscript by Ralph Armbruster-Sandoval -- teaching the black/brown metropolis., June 2004 (Box 1, Folder 21)
      Teaching the Black/Brown Metropolis: Race, Class, and Resistance in the city- written by Ralph Armbruster-Sandoval. Manuscript draft. It is unclear whether it was revised into a published paper.
    - Collected newspaper articles., 1942 October 30-1944 July 07 (Box 2, Folder 1)
      Articles are contemporary with trial and illustrate the widespread sensationalizing of Mexican youth crime.
    - Photographs of defendants' release., 1944 October (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Los Angeles Times Obituaries of three Sleepy Lagoon Defendants (Ysmael Parra, Manuel Reyes, Henry Ynostroza)., 2001 May 21-2008 March 07 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Los Angeles Philharmonic benefit concert., 1943 July 02 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Jazz concert held to raise money for the defendants. Includes names of the original musicians who played.
    - Photographs of McGrath and Levyas family post-Sleepy Lagoon (35 years after the trial)., ca. 1978 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Ben Margolis., ca. 1999 (Box 3, Folder 3)
      Contains copies of programs paying tribute to Margolis, a copy of an interview transcript, a letter about Margolis, and a photograph.
    - Kevin Starr -- article and correspondence., 2002 October 12-2002 October 28 (Box 3, Folder 4)
      Includes copy of Starr's article and McGrath's letters to Kevin Starr's article errors, It also includes his replies
    - Eduardo Pagan -- correspondence., 2003 April 08-2003 April 20 (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Letters about Pagan's misrepresentations of the Sleepy Lagoon Case
    - Illinois Jacquet -- obituary., 2004 July 24 (Box 3, Folder 6)
      One of the Jazz musician who participated in a concert benefit for the Sleepy Lagoon Trial
    - Sleepy Lagoon symposium at UCLA., 2005 May 20-21 (Box 3, Folder 7)
      Announcement card for The Sleepy Lagoon Case: Constitutional Rights and the Struggle for Democracy held May 20-21, 2005.
  - 1.2 Zoot-Suit Media Adaptations., 1978-2008
    This subseries focuses on the play, film, and documentary adaptation of the Sleepy Lagoon Trial and McGrath's collaboration mainly with Valdez.
    - Correspondence -- adaptations of the Sleepy Lagoon trial., 1978 February-September (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Includes Valdez's original letter to McGrath about his idea for a play
    - Correspondence -- rights within adaptations., 1978 April 14-1980 December 23 (Box 3, Folder 9)
      Correspondence about rights to use McGrath as character in play, film and documentary, including legal contracts
    - Zoot Suit play -- first typescript draft., 1977 November 28 (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Zoot Suit play -- second typescript draft., 1978 February 28 (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Zoot Suit play -- final typescript draft., 1978 April 30 (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Mark Taper's Zoot Suit play press release, cast contact list, and Aquarius theater information list., 1978 April (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Revised final., 1978 July 11 (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Zoot Suit film adaptation -- first typescript draft., 1980 June 9 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Zoot Suit film adaptation -- third typescript draft., 1980 October 20 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Zoot Suit Play at the Mark Taper review., 1978 April 24 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Mark Taper Zoot Suit programs production programs., 1978 April-September (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Mark Taper souvenir program, Ephemera of Zoot-Suit play., ca. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Mark Taper souvenir buttons (2)., ca. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Newspaper clippings about the play., 1978 April 16-1978 September 4 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Aquarius Theater production Copies of play program., ca. 1978 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Newspaper reviews of play at the Aquarius Theater., 1978 Sept 27-1979 June 27 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Winter Garden Theater production copies of play program., 1979 March (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Winter Garden Theater production souvenirs, few souvenir buttons., 1979 (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Newspaper reviews of Zoot Suit play., 1978 April-1979 June (Box 5, Folder 1)
      Mainly in Broadway, NY.
    - Zoot Suit play rehearsal photographs., 1978 (Box 5, Folder 2)
      Snapshots of rehearsal including Gordon Davidson, Luis Valdez, Danny Lopez (actually Daniel Valdez?) and Edward James Olmos as well as Chepe
    - Zoot Suit play adaptation programs., 1999-2008 April (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - Photographs Alice McGrath and original play cast with Tyne Daly and Carey McWilliams., 1978-1992 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Photograph of Edward James Olmos as El Pachuco., ca. 1979 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - Pictures of opening night of film Zoot Suit., ca. 1980 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Zoot Suit Motion Picture production., 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Zoot Suit Universal Studios production Souvenir button., 1981 (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Zoot Suit: The Play and the Promise., 1979 (Box 5, Folder 9)
      Includes press release and letter.
    - Zoot Suit: The Play and the Promise -- photographs and slides (taken of television screen)., 1978 (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - The Sleepy Lagoon Murders -- miniseries announcement., 1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
      Article and announcement about the miniseries under development. The New Ingot Company (Larry Schiller) was producing the series with Abby Mann. The series appears to have never developed.
    - The Sleepy Lagoon Murders -- correspondence., 1978 (Box 5, Folder 12)
      Mainly between Alice McGrath and the new Ingot Co., Joan Scott.
    - Zoot Suit and related lectures by Alice McGrath -- correspondence., 1981 (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Zoot Suit and related lectures by Alice McGrath -- ephemera., 1981-1982 (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - From Sleepy Lagoon to Zoot Suit: The Irreverent Path of Alice McGrath -- reviews, correspondence and ephemera., 1997 (Box 5, Folder 15)
      Produced by Bob Giges.
    - Zoot Suit Symposium at the Disney Center., 2004 September 17-30 (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Latino Film Festival Program that featured Zoot Suit film., 1998 October 28-November 1 (Box 5, Folder 17)
    - Correspondence from Manuel Delgado., ca. 1970 (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Newsletter from AM to those involved in Sleepy Lagoon defense., 1978 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Zoot Suite play -- reviews and ephemera., 1977-1997 (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Newspaper articles -- Zoot Suit and Alice McGrath., 1978 (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper articles -- Sleepy Lagoon case and play., 1957 April 30-2001 January 31 (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Articles -- press information about Alice McGrath., 1981 (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Zoot Suit play -- first night programs., 1978 August (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Sanchez, Paul "Zoot Suit" is heritage on stage., 1978 December 17 (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - La Pantera Rosa reception invention., 1979 (Box 6, Folder 8)
      In honor of Zoot Suit play.
    - Zoot Suit play -- photographs at third opening at Aquarius., 1996 (Box 6, Folder 9)
      Alice McGrath holding original program with Luis Valdez, Alice McGrath receiving kiss.
    - Zoot Suit play -- advance critical reviews., 1979 April 21 (Box 6, Folder 10)
    - New York production reviews (photocopies)., 1979 April (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - Zoot Suit play -- ticket stubs., 1979 March 25 (Box 6, Folder 12)
      Opening night March 25, Alan Alda Note March 27, tickets Aquarius March, ticket stub Winter Garden opening night
    - Invitation to reception Mayor Tom Bradley, Assemblymen Richard Alatorre and Art Torres in honor the cast and crew of Zoot Suit., 1978 (Box 6, Folder 13)
    - El Grito, March/April 1979. (Box 6, Folder 14)
      Issue of El Grito includes the article, "Zoot Suite: La Historia Chicana en el Senario."
    - Zoot Suit Winter Garden Theatre souvenir program., ca. 1979 (Box 6, Folder 15)
    - Articles -- Zoot Suit play and Alice McGrath., 1978 March-1982 December (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - Zoot Suit Motion Picture -- articles about possible production., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 17)
    - Zoot Suit Motion Picture -- newspaper articles., 1979-1990 May (Box 6, Folder 18)
- 2. Personal papers., 1943-2006
  Contains items of personal interest to Alice McGrath including correspondence, clippings regarding personal friends or family, and ephemera from McGrath's personal life.
  - 2.1 Correspondence., 1943-2005
    Contains correspondence between McGrath, colleagues, and family. Also includes clippings and ephemera related to the people with whom she had correspondence.
    - McWilliams, Carey., 1943 (Box 6, Folder 19)
    - McWilliams, Carey., 1970 (Box 6, Folder 20)
      Includes photographs of Alice McGrath
    - McWilliams, Carey., 1970 (Box 6, Folder 21)
    - McWilliams, Iris., 1980 (Box 6, Folder 22)
    - Libraries and publishing companies -- about Carey McWilliams's book,North from Mexico., 1970 (Box 6, Folder 23)
    - From Alice McGrath -- about Carey McWilliams., 1970 (Box 6, Folder 24)
    - Symposium with Carey McWilliams., 1979 November 7 (Box 6, Folder 25)
      Held at Ventura College with Carey McWilliams and Alice McGrath and moderated by Rene Rodriguez.
    - Photographs -- Mayor Tom Bradley commendation ceremony to honor McWilliams., 1979 (Box 6, Folder 26)
      Photographs include Alice McGrath, Carey McWilliams, Luiz Valdez and Tom Bradley
    - Photographs -- Alice McGrath speaking at Carey McWilliams's class at UCLA., 1978 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Clippings -- Carey McWilliams., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 2)
      Includes articles about McWilliams as well as those he authored.
    - Photographs -- Carey McWilliams' memorial service at UCLA., 1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
    - Reviews --American Prophet: The Life and Work of Carey McWilliams by Peter Richardson., 2005 (Box 7, Folder 4)
    - Carey Williams: the Great Exception. Los Angeles: KFPK., 1979 (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - Articles -- about Carey McWilliams., 1984 (Box 7, Folder 6)
      Includes an entry Alice McGrath wrote on Carey McWilliams for the Encyclopedia Americana as other articles she wrote about him.
    - Ephemera -- Carey McWilliams (posthumous)., 1980 (Box 7, Folder 7)
      Folder consists predominantly of memorials and obituaries.
    - Southern California Library for Social Studies and Research., 1947 (Box 7, Folder 8)
      Includes programs and invitation to the 1993 awards dinner at the library.
    - Correspondence -- W.E.B. and Shirley DuBois., 1956 (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - Invitations -- dinner to honor W.E.B. DuBois., 1953 (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - Photographs -- W.E.B DuBois., 1956 (Box 7, Folder 11)
      One photograph is inscribed to Alice McGrath by W.E.B. DuBois.
    - Thank you note -- from Stud Terkel., ca. 1984 (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - Photographs -- E. P. Thompson and Alice McGrath., 1991 May (Box 7, Folder 13)
      Photograph was taken at E.P. Thompson's country home in England.
    - Correspondence -- various (folder 1 of 2)., 1958-2002 (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - Correspondence -- various (folder 1 of 2)., 1958-2002 (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - Programs from the Apollo Theater and Gallery Theater., ca. 1989-2002 (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - Correspondence -- various., 1984 (Box 7, Folder 17)
      Predominantly notes or forms. One refers to package AM sent her son while he was in prison.
    - Correspondence -- Dan Schechter., 1990 (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - Correspondence -- Dan Schechter., 1991 (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - Correspondence -- Dan Schechter., 1992 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Correspondence -- Dan Schechter., 1993 (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - Photographs -- Dan Schechter while protesting., ca. 1990 (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Poems by and from Dan Schechter., 1991 (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Clippings -- Dan Schechter's protests and arrest., 1991 June 7 (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - Dan Schechter's statements about protests and arrests., 1990-1991 (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - Dan Schechter's prison newsletters., 1991 (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - Dan Schechter open letter., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - Dan Schechter's writings on various causes, government action, and civil disobedience., 1989 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - 2.2 Writings., 1955-2001
    - The Perpetual Bourgeois., 1955 (Box 8, Folder 10)
      Draft of poem by Alice McGrath published in Coastlines's first issue in Spring 1955.
    - Social and Business Hints for the Man on the Way Down., after 1961 (Box 8, Folder 11)
      Unpublished manuscript draft written by Alice McGrath, illustrations by Chris Jenkyns.
    - College papers written by Alice McGrath., 1965 (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - Publishing correspondence., 1984-1986 (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - Clippings about Alice McGrath's class at Ventura College., 1984 (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - Alice McGrath's music log., 1970 (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - McGrath's newspaper opinion pieces., 1976-2001 (Box 8, Folder 16)